Today's דף daf is פז, Pey Zayin, 87. We begin at the
top of פז. Pey Zayin. And basically the משנה Mishnah
had
been talking about a well that runs between two courtyards, and in
order for each courtyard to use it, you can't be using from
the other side or water from the other side. So there's no
way you're really going to divide the water, but what do you
need sort of symbolically to do that? So according to the חכמים,
Chachamim, you needed to put some type of a מחיצה mechitzah inside
of the well, and we debated exactly how deep and how much
into the water. And according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the wall
that ran on top of the well, over the well on top,
actually would work, even though it didn't go in the well, we
would view it as though it extends in and it divided the
water. And the גמרא Gemara says that that's similar or the same,
quote-unquote, as the position of חנניה בן עקביא, Chananya ben Akavya, who
also is very lenient when it comes to walls or מחיצות mechitzos
over water. As we know, there's a lot of leniency to allow
this type of an extended מחיצה mechitzah into water because, you know,
you have need for water access. And we're going to see later
today or tomorrow that primarily when it's about drawing water as opposed
to putting stuff into the water—we discussed the other day that תוספות
Tosafot talks about having your bathrooms over these bodies of water, which
explains a lot of the health issues in the Middle Ages, but
primarily when it was more about drawing the water and access to
water, חז"ל Chazal understood the great importance of that and they were
more lenient. So what is this leniency of חנניה בן עקביא? Chananya
ben Akavya? So normally we say that if you've got a platform
extending outside of your building over a body of water and you
want a hole in it and to draw water from it, the
first leniency that everybody agrees on is if you make a booth
like מחיצות mechitzos around the hole above it or below it, we
view it as if they go all the way down into the
water. Normally we don't extend מחיצות mechitzos down all the way, they
have to be connected to the ground, but here we view it
as though it does. חנניה בן עקביא's Chananya ben Akavya statement was
even more lenient and he said that if you've got just your
whole platform is ארבע אמות arba amos by ארבע אמות, arba amos,
which is twenty-four טפחים, tefachim, and therefore your hole is four by
four טפחים tefachim because that's the minimum size you need for רשות
היחיד, Reshus HaYachid, then you have עשרה טפחים asara tefachim in each
direction here and you don't even need to build any walls because
you view it as if each one of those sides bends down.
So here's your hole, right, and you view it as though all
of the sides have bent down around the hole. And here's your
עשרה טפחים asara tefachim and here's your ten and here's your ten
and here's your ten, right? So you imaginarily view it as if
it had all bent down and you don't even need to make
walls around it in that case and you can just lower your
bucket and fill it up. Okay, and that's what חנניה בן עקביא
Chananya ben Akavya says. So we're going to pick up here from
that in the גמרא. Gemara.
Can you use the same hole to draw water and as a
bathroom?
Well, the גמרא Gemara is going to say primarily they probably did.
But anyway, the גמרא Gemara is going to speak that it's basically
about drawing water. We'll see about that a little bit later, but
right now it has yet to discuss and distinguish that way. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. We'll take it from the top
of פז עמוד א, Pey Zayin Amud Aleph, we'll reread the last
line we read yesterday. אמר ליה אביי. Amar leh Abaye. So אביי
Abaye said to this idea, statement, that this was the same as
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of the משנה. Mishnah. ודילמא לא היא. U-dilma
lo hi. Maybe it's not really this חנניה Chananya statement is not
really, you know, the same basic approach as רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
in the משנה. Mishnah. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה התם. Ad
kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Yehuda hatam.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says you use the wall over the
well and you view it as extending into the well, fine, he
says you extend the wall down, even if it's over the well.
אבל כוף וגוד, Aval kuff ve-gud, but to bend the wall and
then extend it down like we just demonstrated, לא, lo,
he, you know, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda wouldn't go that far. ועד
כאן לא קאמר חנניה בן עקביא התם. Ve-ad kan lo ka-amar Chananya
ben Akavya hatam. חנניה בן עקביא Chananya ben Akavya true is very
lenient, but maybe he only said it there, אלא בימא של טבריה.
ela be-yama shel Tiveria. What we're going to see at the end
of today's דף daf is that this was a specific ruling in
Tiberius over the כנרת, Kinneret, right? כנרת, Kinneret, yeah.
הואיל ויש לו אגניים, Ho'il ve-yesh lo agnaim, because it has actually
banks or—ועיירות ve-ayarot and towns
or villages וקרפיפות ve-karfifot and like yards מקיפות אותה makifot otah surrounding
it. I'll discuss that in a minute. אבל בשאר מימות לא אמר.
Aval bishar meimot lo amar.
Not by other waters. So it seems the key there, the banks,
right? If you actually have something that is has more, you know,
the water is more like this, right, so and it's got banks,
it's not just in a well, but it's got banks, then to
some degree you can use the part above the water, right, as
some type of a beginning of a מחיצה. mechitzah. The problem is
that the same is true about a well; if a well isn't
totally full, you have that as well, as well. So it sounds
like, but it's more also that, you know, that it is maybe
there's like a tremendous, either there's a combination of there's a tremendous
amount of need for it or because it's more in the middle
of some inhabited space it's more considered to be like a רשות
היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. It's not exactly clear. Why that matters so much.
רש״י Rashi *Rashi* emphasizes the banks. רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says that because
of the banks, it's already the beginning of a מחיצה *Mechitza*, but
again I'm not exactly sure why that is so much different than
the case of the well, I must admit. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* understands again maybe the combination of a quasi-מחיצה *Mechitza* and just
the need surrounding the Tiberias was so great that he had to
give a better a greater allowance. As opposed to a normal case
of a normal well.
Yeah, I don't really get let's say another city that, other towns.
I imagine that if you had another scenario that was similar to
that it would be the same. But again, whether the emphasis here
is like I said again, עיירות *ayarot* and קרפיפות *karpifot* are like
villages and lots, you know, like yards. So I don't know how
that's relevant to viewing it as a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid *Reshus
HaYachid*, you know, maybe what it's relevant to is somehow the degree
of need that there was to come up with a היתר *heter*,
but I really don't know how to fully, you know, translate that
into why that's directly relevant. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
has a little bit fun with this bending of the plank. So
let's take a look. אמר amar אביי *Amar Abaye*, said אביי *Abaye*:
ולדברי רבי חנניה בן עקביא Chananya ben Akavia *U'ledivrei Rabbi Chanania ben
Akavia*, according to רבי חנניה Chananya בן עקביא *Rabbi Chanania ben Akavia*
that you can bend, היתה סמוכה לכותל בפחות מג׳ טפחים tefachim. *haita
smucha lekoseil bepachas migimel tefachim*, let's say it was not attached to
the wall. Don't ask me how it was suspended, maybe on some
type of like you know protrusion, and if it was therefore within
three of the wall, this plank, צריכה ארבע אמות amot, *tzricha arba
amot*, it still has to be four אמות amot, *amot* wide and
ורחבה ארבע אמות amot? *v'rachba arba amot* wide, 24 טפחים tefachim *tefachim*,
ורחבה אחת עשרה ומשהו *v'rachba achas esrei umashehu*, but it doesn't have
to be four אמות amot *amot* in the other direction, it only
has to be four אמות amot? *amot* long, but it only has
to be eleven טפחים four tefachim *tefachim* and a little bit wide.
Why is that? Because and you see why I brought my make
sure I have a good working pen with me today, although this
is garbage. Anyway, so here's your wall.
I'm trying to think about how a good way to show this.
Anyway, here's your wall, okay. Now if you actually have this thing
held out here, not directly against the wall, it's within three of
the wall, okay. So you start to see what I'm doing? It's
like protruding out from the wall, it's within three of the wall.
Then what you're going to do is, you're going to do, here's
what you're going to do, you only have to
you don't have to create
what don't you have to do?
Hold on. If you have this, you have a little insert here,
let's just draw what you've got. You've got a cut out a
little bit here. So now you've got a virtual hole, right? That
is four by four, okay? Right? You've got your .299 and you've
got one your you have your 1.1 little cut out hole. That's
going to be your hole, okay? Most of it from the space
before you get to the plank. Is that clear what I'm drawing?
Okay, so so, therefore, what you really just have to do is
you've got to bend down this wall and bend down that wall.
So really it doesn't have to go out so much, right? Because
you just need once you're going to bend it down here, if
you've got it like this and you know the rest here is
the space to the wall, okay, so if you bend this down,
right, that's okay, then you've got your ten טפחים four tefachim. *tefachim*.
Now how about the fact that the wall doesn't go four טפחים
tefachim *tefachim* wide? Well it doesn't matter, it's less than three, so
you say לבוד lavud *lavud*. So it's as if you've got the
whole thing as a wall. All right, I'm not doing three dimensions
so well, but I think you see the point.
So here
too, if you bend that down, this has to be ten טפחים
tefachim *tefachim*, but this, the cutout you made, was only 1.1, right?
And the other 2.9 are in open space to the wall, and
that's as if it reaches the end. So now flatten that out.
So if you flatten that out, you've
got
ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* here, ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* here, right? And
this whole thing is 1.1.
And then you're going to flatten it, yes, people with me here?
You're going to flatten it and then you're going to get the
other 2.9 as if it's connected to the wall. But then of
course you need this side. So this side has to be ten
טפחים tefachim *tefachim* like that, right? So because you need the fourth
wall.
So therefore in that case, right, and assuming therefore you're going to
deal with not a bun-shaped plank but a, you know, but a
normal shaped plank, so what's the plank going to be? It's going
to be if this is so this is going to be here
ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* plus the 1.1 that you cut out. So
this direction it's going to be eleven טפחים tefachim *tefachim* point you
know plus .1, right? And here ten טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*, four and
ten, it's going to be 24 טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*
or four אמות *amot*. So that's what he says. If you've got
it separate from the wall three or less than three, whatever, 2.9,
you need it only to be you need it still to be
the four אמות *amot* this way so you can bend this down,
but you need this only to be the 1.1 and the ten,
the 11.1 טפחים tefachim? *tefachim* and you bend that one down.
That was I just got a text message, this camera needs to
aim a bit to the
right to see the board. Okay.
Yeah, no, this is all just imaginary. They're just having fun with
the math. No, this isn't, it's nothing actual here. Okay, so it
says like this.
Okay, so הייתה סמוכה לכותל פחות מג' טפחים tefachim? צריך שיאורכה ארבע
אמות tzarich she'orkah arbah amot ורוחבה אחד עשר ומשהו. verochvah achad asar
umasheyhu. הייתה זקופה, hayetah zekufah,
let's say what you did actually was that you held up this
plank against somehow in midair and you held it up vertically. צריך
שגובה עשרה טפחים tzarich shegovah asarah tefachim ורוחבה ז' טפחים ושני משהוים.
verochvah zayin tefachim ushnei masheyhuim.
This is easier somehow. Okay, so as opposed to this, here what
you've done is you basically have your building like this, your wall
like this, and you have somehow extended out here a vertical, you
know, a vertical wall. Okay, so I'm trying to think about what
like a cross, let's do a cross-section of it, like a side
view of it and a front view of it. Where am I?
A side view of it would be this is, you know,
a side view of it. Trying to think about how this looks.
Okay,
anyway, somehow here is, not so great as a side view. But
anyway, here's your plank and here's your, here's your wall, okay? And
this is, so this is going to be, so it's like this.
You're going to want to lower your bucket down here. All right?
You've got your planks vertical out of the wall. This is within
ג' טפחים gimel tefachim in order to say לבוד lavud as if
it's connected, this is going to be 2.9 טפחים. tefachim Now you've
already got this ten טפחים tefachim high. So you already have your
facing wall. So you have one wall is the wall of your
building, you've got this plank out there that's your facing wall. All
you've got to do is bend it in a little bit, right?
And if you could bend it in a little bit, then, then
you've got this, that if this is 1.1 and then after bending
in it's 2.9, you've got your four טפחים tefachim and you're good.
Is that thing clear? Within ג' טפחים gimel tefachim of the wall.
So it's not within ג' טפחים gimel tefachim actually, it is, I'm
sorry. The whole distance from the wall is four טפחים. tefachim So
this is again your four by four. Okay? But now you bend
in, you virtually bend in the sides of it, right? If you
actually had it looking like that, right, bent in, it would be
perfect. You have ten טפחים tefachim? high, one wall, two walls. After
you bend it in it's, you know, it's 1.1 plus the 2.9,
it's like it's all connected. So if you don't have it bent
and you have it flat, then you have ten טפחים tefachim high
by 4 plus 1.1,
this is the part you're going to bend, and this is the
part you're going to bend, right? 1.1. That's the size of, that's
what the plank that you have. Is that clear? So you put
it parallel to the wall, you bend on the dotted lines, then
afterwards there's 2.9 from these edges to the wall and there's your
booth, okay? So that's what the
גמרא Gemara,
says. הייתה זקופה, hayetah zekufah, צריך שגובה עשרה טפחים tzarich shegovah asarah
tefachim it has to be ten טפחים tefachim high, ורוחבה ז' טפחים
ושני משהוים verochvah zayin tefachim ushnei masheyhuim and the width is seven
טפחים tefachim and two little bits. So that's the point one that
I did in my, in my description. Okay,
ולמנפח, ulemanpach, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, amar Rav Huna breih
deRav Yehoshua, הייתה עומדת בקרן זוית. hayetah omedet bekeren zavit. Now let's
say actually the, where you're lowering down your bucket is right by
where the wall sort of at a corner of the wall. That's
good, so the wall's already providing you two out of the four
walls. צריך שגובה עשרה טפחים tzarich shegovah asarah tefachim ורוחבה ב' טפחים
ושני משהוים. verochvah bet tefachim ushnei masheyhuim. What you're going to do
is you're going to put this plank also somehow suspended in midair
right here at the, you've got, you've got your building, right,
you've got these two corners of the wall here. So and you're
going to lower your bucket down here. So you've already got two
corners, right? You're coming here at the building. You've got to get
two more corners. You've got to get basically this little corner, you
know, right? You've got to get those other two. Well, that's easy.
If you have here 1.1 and 1.1 and you situate it within
2.9,
you've created the other two walls. Is that sort of clear? You've
got your plank, it's ten טפחים tefachim. high and
it's 1.1 and 1.1. The whole thing here is 2.2. You fold
it, right? and you get that plank to look like this.
Okay, you've folded that. And you situate that right by the corner
of the, of the building, at the corner of the building. And
you situate what you folded right there, okay? And that goes 1.1
in each direction and you situate it within four, so this is
2.9 and that's your booth essentially and that's your four walls and
you lower.
The corners of two buildings, right, two buildings intersecting. Okay, so הייסמה
דמשכחן בצוותא דצריך גבוה עשרה טפחים, Haysema demishkachan b'tzavta d'tzarich gavoah asarah
tefachim, the
plank has to be עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim high ורוחבה בי טפחים
ומשני משהו v'rochvah bei tefachim u'mishnei mashehu
and the width two and a little bit. ואלא הא דתניא V'ela
ha d'tanya רב חנניה בן עקביא Rav Chananya ben Akavya אומר omer
גזוסטרא שיש בה ארבע אמות על ארבע אמות חוקק בה ארבע על
ארבע וממלא gezustra sheyesh bah arba amot al arba amot chokek bah
arba al arba umemalei היכי משכחת לה? heichi mishkachat lah? So what
רב חנניה בן עקביא Rav Chananya ben Akavya said, which is that
you needed four by four אמות, you've given brilliant ways of configuring
it that you need a lot less, right? If you hold it
with 2.9 away from the wall, you're always going to need less
than four by four אמות, depending on how you hold it horizontal
and vertical or whatever. When do you ever need four by four
אמות? So the simple answer would be fine, when it's connected directly
to the wall. You haven't suspended it in
mid-air, because all of these are like very interesting hypotheticals, but his
case is a simpler case. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. When do you ever need really four אמות by four אמות?
דעבידה כאסיניתא, D'avida k'asita, you make it
like a mortar basically, which means that it
is
Rashi basically says the opposite. Rather than just you didn't suspend it
in mid-air, רשי Rashi actually says the case is is that it
was suspended way out there and it was more than ארבעה טפחים
arba'ah tefachim away. So here's your wall, right, the board you have
is way out here, somehow it's suspended way out, and you can't
use the wall. It's five טפחים tefachim away or more than whatever,
more than three. So you can't use the wall and since you
can't use the wall you have to use only the plank to
make all four sides. The easier answer is just it's not suspended
at all, a common case where it's connected to the wall. It
has to be four by four. If you're able to situate it
so that you can use לבוד lavud. to your advantage, then געזונטערהייט.
gezunterheit. All right. Anyway, that's the end of that. The גמרא, Gemara
as I said, seems to have had fun. I don't know if
you all had as much fun. I enjoyed it. Seems to have
had fun imagining how you could bend, once you're talking about imaginarily
bending a plank, how could we do interesting
configurations and make the advantage, use the advantage of לבוד. lavud Mr.
Corn, you've got to sign. Yeah, right, that was amazing, my drawings,
I must say. Okay, so let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishna. אמת המים, Amas hamayim, now, back to the idea of
finding a way to use a virtual wall to allow you access
to water, which is what the theme is.
אמת המים, Amas hamayim, you have
a canal or somehow a
not a river, but what aqueduct, thank you, that passes through your
חצר. chatzer. אין ממלאין
הימנה בשבת, Ein memalin heimah b'Shabbat, you can't draw from it on
שבת. Shabbat. Why? Because it's a כרמלית. carmelit. Now here's what you
have to know. If it is to be a כרמלית, carmelit, to
be its own separate domain and not just considered like part of
the floor of the yard, which is now רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
because it's surrounded by walls, to be its own separate domain it
has to be ten deep and four wide. Then it's its own
separate domain, it's a כרמלית, carmelit, and then you can't draw water
from it into your yard on שבת. Shabbat. And then the question
is going to be also how do you make it walls, essentially,
to turn this into a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid so you can
draw water from it on שבת? Shabbat? So the same idea of
making walls, except whereas in the last משנה Mishna the problem was
it was a well, which was a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, because
it was very straight and deep, this
which is not a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid? it's a כרמלית, carmelit,
so the well case the question was if we're competing because it's
between two courtyards. How do we divide my courtyard and your courtyard?
Here, this is a כרמלית, carmelit, and because it's a כרמלית carmelit
the question is how are we going to make walls to turn
it into a רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid Now what I am waiting
for somebody to ask is, I don't understand, why is this a
כרמלית? carmelit? Why isn't this just a long well? Okay? If your
well in your חצר chatzer which is ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim wide
and עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim deep, even though it's got all this
water in it, is called a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. because it's
four by ten, right, here it is in your חצר, chatzer, okay,
so if you have in your חצר chatzer your
this aqueduct passing through, okay, so we set, I've told you and
the משנה Mishna is going to say that it's only if it's
less than ten deep or less than four wide, it's just part
of the רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid? What makes it a כרמלית carmelit
is that it is ten deep and four wide. Well why isn't
that just a nice long well? Why isn't that a רשות היחיד?
reshut hayachid. Yes? Only two walls. Ah, it only has two walls.
What about the fact that somewhere it ends? So somewhere maybe it's
got a wall here. It's passing through another רשות. reshut. Ah, so
that's a good question. So there's actually an interesting debate why this
is not a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid? Some say that we're talking
about that the slope of the walls is not sharp, right? If
the slope is gradual, as you remember, it doesn't count as a
wall. Remember that?
And in that case why would it not be part of the
רשות היחיד?
reshus hayachid, Well because eventually it gets to ten deep, it's just
they're not called walls. The better answer, which is what the מאירי
Meiri says, more or less what you said, is that these walls
are
I also thought what Michael said, which is even if they're not
so far away normally we might say that those are legitimate walls.
What happens if you've got a רשות הרבים reshus harabim here? How
can you call this a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid right, that sort
of runs all the way through? Now, maybe why not? Why can't
you have a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid in the middle of a
רשות הרבים? reshus harabim? But anyway, at least rabbinically this is a
כרמלית, karmelis, because at least as you're experiencing it here it only
has two walls. And therefore your goal to turn it into a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid is to make walls for it here and
here. And then you're going to turn it into a רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid and be able to use it, to use it. Yes.
Of course you have cases of a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. in
the middle of a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
Right. Right, right, right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I don't think running
through a רשות הרבים reshus harabim is enough to make the argument.
Let's look at the משנה mishna therefore. אמה של מים שהיא עוברת
בחצר, amma shel mayim shehi overes b'chatzer, so it's going through the
courtyard. אין ממלאין
הימנה בשבת אלא אם כן עשו לה מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים בכניסה
וביציאה. ein memalin heimena b'shabbos ela im ken asu la mechitzah gevoha
asara tefachim bechnisa uvyetziah. You have to make some type of a
divider or wall where it comes in and out of the courtyard,
10 טפחים tefachim high, and presumably into the banks of the aqueduct
itself. You have to go under the lip of the aqueduct like
you had to do by the well. רבי יהודה אומר כותל שעל
גבה צידון משום מחיצה הוא. Rabbi Yehuda omer kotel she'al gaba tzedon
mishum mechitzah hu. He needs it. It's got the normal wall of
the courtyard. Every courtyard, somehow this runs under, every courtyard has its
own wall, I guess. So he says it's already got a wall.
This wall counts, whereas the חכמים chachamim say like they said by
the well that you have to make the wall actually underground. You
have to make the wall into the actual aqueduct itself. Okay? Is
that debate clear? He says you've just got your normal
well. So you've got your normal wall, that counts as the wall.
Right? The side view is like this. Right?
Here's
your wall of the courtyard, and here is the water that's running
through the courtyard. Okay, and the wall is over it. So that's
the water running through. So he says, trying to do this, right?
So
that's what it looks like. So he says why doesn't the wall
just count, whereas the חכמים chachamim say no, you actually have to
stick a divider down into the actual aqueduct itself. Okay. All right.
So is that clear? Is that what we're talking about? All right.
So he says
like this. So it's the same רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of the
previous משנה. mishna. He said the same thing about the well. The
wall that goes on top counts. You don't actually have to make
a wall into the actual thing itself. So אמר רבי יהודה. amar
Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda tries to prove his point.
אמר רבי
יהודה מעשה באמה של אבל, amar Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh b'amma shel avel,
that's in a city that was near, I think ציפורי. Tzipori. We're
going to find out in a minute. Where was it near? Yeah,
ציפורי. Tzipori. So it had this
aqueduct שהיו ממלאין ממנה על פי זקנים בשבת. shehayu memalin mimena al
pi zkenim b'shabbos. They would draw water from it on שבת shabbos
even though it did not have a new wall into the aqueduct
itself. Presumably because they used the wall that went over it, that
was the wall of the courtyard. אמרו לו, amru lo, the sages
said back to him, מפני שלא היה בה כשיעור, mipnei shelo haya
ba kashiyur, that wasn't really a כרמלית. karmelis. It wasn't 10 deep
or it wasn't four wide and therefore you didn't need any of
this because that was just part of the רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
But when it really is its own domain, you need to put
a wall into the water itself, or
into the depth, not on top of it. Let's take a look.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Our rabbis taught. עשו לה בכניסה ולא עשו
לה ביציאה, asu la bechnisa velo asu la byetziah, if you did
it in the entrance of the courtyard but not the exit. עשו
לה ביציאה ולא עשו לה בכניסה, asu la byetziah velo asu la
bechnisa, or the exit not the entrance. אין ממלאין הימנה בשבת, ein
memalin heimena b'shabbos, you can't draw from it. אלא אם כן עשו
לה מחיצה עשרה טפחים ביציאה ובכניסה. ela im ken asu la mechitzah
asara tefachim byetziah ubechnisa. It has to be both at the entrance
and the exit. רבי יהודה אומר כותל שעל גבה צידון משום מחיצה
הוא. Rabbi Yehuda omer kotel she'al gaba tzedon mishum mechitzah hu. He
needs to put a new divider into the aqueduct itself. The wall
that runs on top of it can count. The same thing he
said by the well he's saying here by the aqueduct. אמר רבי
יהודה מעשה באמת המים שהייתה באה מאבל לציפורי. amar Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh
b'amas hamayim shehaysa ba me'avel l'tzipori. There was an aqueduct that went
from אבל Abel to ציפורי. Tzipori. Steinsaltz has a nice little picture.
They're very close to one another. והיו ממלאין הימנה בשבת על פי
זקנים, vehayu memalin heimena b'shabbos al pi zkenim, and they would draw
water from it even though it was did not have a special
divider put into it. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him,
משם ראיה, misham raya, from there you want to bring a proof?
מפני שלא הייתה עמוקה עשרה טפחים ורוחב ארבעה, mipnei shelo hayesa amuka
asara tefachim verochav arba'a, and there explicitly are the dimensions. If it
wasn't 10 deep and four wide it's part of the רשות היחיד.
Reshut Hayachid, It is not its own domain. It is not its
own כרמלית. karmelis. Okay.
So that's the same debate we had before whether the wall above
the water that goes straight over is enough or does it have
to actually go into the depth of that place where the water
is running. I mean here though, it's to make it into a
רשות היחיד, Reshut Hayachid. whereas before it was to divide it between
two courtyards. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא. Baraisa.
אמת המים העוברת בין החלונות, Amat hamayim ha'overes bein hachalonos, you have
an aqueduct going between two windows, meaning you've got an aqueduct going
in the middle like in an alleyway and the houses are on
two sides of the street and it's between the two windows or
between the two houses.
פחות מג' משלשל דלי וממלא, Pachus migimmel meshalshel deli umemale, less than
three טפחים, tefachim you can lower down a bucket and fill it.
ג', Gimmel, three טפחים, tefachim, אין משלשל דלי וממלא, ein meshalshel deli
umemale, you cannot lower down a bucket. Now, what is three טפחים?
tefachim. The גמרא Gemara wants to know.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, פחות מארבעה משלשל דלי וממלא, pachus
me'arba'ah meshalshel deli umemale, less than four you can fill a bucket.
ארבעה אין משלשל דלי וממלא, arba'ah ein meshalshel deli umemale, four you
cannot. Now you might remember that there is a debate of תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel whether לבוד lavud. is
three or four. That seems to be the same debate here, so
they're trying to say something about לבוד. lavud? But what are they
saying about לבוד?
lavud I mean, they're describing a scenario that you've got, you know,
your two buildings, okay I
need to do some more drawing, you've got your two buildings on
the two side and you've got an aqueduct running through them and
the question is, can you lower down your bucket and fill it
up? So what's three טפחים? tefachim Three טפחים tefachim to the wall?
Fine, so then use the wall to the building, it still only
has two walls, it doesn't have four walls, where is three טפחים
tefachim, going to matter to determine whether I can lower my bucket
down and fill it up? So the גמרא's Gemara going to have
three explanations for this, let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, what are we talking about? אילימא באמת המים
גופא, ilima be'amas hamayim gufa, whether the aqueduct itself is three טפחים
tefachim. or not, because remember, a minute ago we said wide, a
minute ago we said if it's not four wide by ten deep,
it's not its own רשות, reshut, it's part of the רשות היחיד.
Reshut Hayachid, So maybe that's what they're debating, what is the minimum
width for it to be considered its own רשות, reshut, three טפחים
tefachim or four טפחים? tefachim Okay, so that's what they're debating. ואלא
הא דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, ve'ela ha dechi ata
Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, and maybe actually there's a position that
says that once it's more than three טפחים tefachim or three טפחים
tefachim or more, it's its own domain, as opposed to the four
טפחים tefachim which is what we've been saying. ואלא הא דכי אתא
רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, ve'ela ha dechi ata Rav Dimi amar
Rabbi Yochanan, but one minute, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he said in the name of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, אין כרמלית פחותה מארבעה, ein Karmelit pechusah me'arba'ah,
that for something to be a כרמלית Karmelit it has to be
at least four טפחים. tefachim, And you're trying to say now that
maybe the issue is whether this aqueduct is three טפחים tefachim or
four טפחים tefachim and according to one opinion three טפחים Tefachim is
enough to make it its own domain. לימא כתנאי איתמרה? leima ketannai
ismarah? So when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that a כרמלית Karmelit
has to be four טפחים, is he saying one side of a
debate of תנאים? Tannaim? It sounded like it was a universally agreed
that a כרמלית Karmelit has to be four טפחים. So what is
this opinion that three טפחים makes a difference? אלא באגפה ולהחליף. ela
be'agappah ulehachlif.
So what we're talking about is not the size of a כרמלית
Karmelit but rather the size of a מקום פטור. makom patur. What
you want to do is the following, here's the
banks, okay, and this bank alongside the aqueduct, if it is less
than according to one opinion three, or less than four according to
the other opinion, it is a מקום פטור. makom patur. Remember מקום
פטור makom patur like a little space that's not even ארבעה על
ארבעה טפחים arba'ah al arba'ah tefachim and therefore even though this is
a כרמלית Karmelit and your house is a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid
if the bank is a מקום פטור, makom patur,
what can you do with a מקום פטור? makom patur? You can
lower your bucket down onto the מקום פטור, makom patur, have maybe
some guy here waiting for it, he fills it up from the
כרמלית, Karmelit, brings it back to the מקום פטור makom patur and
then you raise up your bucket.
You can do that.
Now normally you can put from any domain onto מקום פטור makom
patur and take back, but you can't use it as a cheat
and go back to the other domain. So that's what the גמרא's
Gemara going to ask. But it's saying maybe that's what's being debated
here, whether a מקום פטור makom patur is less than four or
less than three. Now even that's a big issue because why should
that be debated? We've always said that four טפחים is the key
for defining a separate domain. So the same way a כרמלית Karmelit
presumably everybody agrees is four טפחים, presumably a מקום פטור makom patur
everybody agrees is less than four טפחים. But here the גמרא Gemara
is saying no, maybe that's what they debate, מקום פטור makom patur
is it less than four or less than three? So let's take
a look.
That shouldn't be saying that.
Well let's take a look, I
agree. אלא באגפה ולהחליף, ela be'agappah ulehachlif, it's the banks and to
exchange, meaning to lower the bucket onto the bank and then from
the bank into the water. והא כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי
יוחנן, veha ke'asi Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, besides that, a, we'd
be debating three or four is a מקום פטור, makom patur, since
when are you allowed to cheat that way? והא כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, veha ke'asi Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, again
רב דימי Rav Dimi said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, מקום שאין בו ארבעה על ארבעה, makom she'ein bo arba'ah al
arba'ah, it's less than four by four, so number one the size
is four, but nevertheless what's even more relevant is
מותר לבני רשות היחיד ולבני רשות הרבים לכתף עליו, muttar livnei Reshut
Hayachid velivnei Reshut Harabbim lechatef alav, so you have this place that's
like in a, I don't know like I said, like a post
office box. that less than four by four, it’s a מקום פטור,
makom patur, it’s in the middle of the street, whatever, both the
people of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and רשות היחיד reshus hayachid can
lay their burdens on it, like take the burden off of the
shoulder, that’s what the word לכתף likatef means. So you can go
from either domain onto it, because it’s a מקום פטור. makom patur.
ובלבד שלא יחליפו, ubilvad shelo yachlifu, but you can’t go from רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid to the מקום פטור makom patur and from the
מקום פטור makom patur to the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So even
if this were a מקום פטור makom patur and there was a
debate of three or four, since when can you go from רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid through מקום פטור makom patur to a כרמלית? karmelis?
You’re not allowed to cheat like that. So the גמרא Gemara says:
התם רשויות
דאורייתא. hosam reshuyos d’oraysa.
No, when are you not allowed to cheat through the מקום פטור
makom patur and go, you know, use it to get to the
other domain? That’s if you’re going from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to
a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or the reverse, where it’s biblical, that
if you were to go straight it would be a biblical violation
of שבת. Shabbos. הכא רשויות דרבנן. hacha reshuyos d’rabonon. Here it’s rabbinic.
Here you’ve got your כרמלית. karmelis. So therefore even if you were
to go straight from your house to the כרמלית, karmelis, it would
only be a rabbinic transgression. And therefore we let you get access
to the כרמלית karmelis through the מקום פטור. makom patur. Now the
גמרא Gemara is not going to stick with this, but according to
this now the debate is, is this a מקום פטור makom patur
when it’s less than four or less than three? And everybody assumes
you can get access to the כרמלית karmelis through the מקום פטור.
makom patur. So the גמרא Gemara is not going to like this.
So the גמרא Gemara. says: והא רבי יוחנן ברשויות דרבנן נמי אמר.
ve’ha Rabbi Yochanan bi’reshuyos d’rabonon nami amar. When רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says you can’t go through a מקום פטור makom patur to get
to another space, he talks about even rabbinic רשויות. reshuyos. How do
you know it? דתניא di’tanya or whatever, not exactly דתניא di’tanya what
do we have here it’s תנן. tnan. כותל שבין שתי חצרות, kosel
she’bein shtei chatzeiros, גבוה עשרה טפחים, gavo’a asara tefachim, right this was
a משנה mishna we had about a week ago. If you have
this wall between two courtyards, ten טפחים high, ורוחב ארבעה, ve’rochav arba’an,
four טפחים wide. So מערבין שנים ואין מערבין אחד. me’arvin shnayim ve’ein
me’arvin echad. Remember that משנה? mishna? That divides the courtyards you can’t
make one עירוב eruv or you can’t make them one עירוב. eruv.
It doesn’t really matter how wide it is not to make one
עירוב, eruv, it matters that it’s ten high. The width we’ll get
to.
היה בראשו פירות, haya berosho peiros, if it had fruit on top,
so it’s ten high and four wide, it’s its own רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid, this wall and has fruit on top of it, but
it’s right between the two courtyards, so the two courtyards are both
essentially competing, but it’s its own domain, it’s ten by four. אלו
עולים מכאן ואוכלים ואלו עולים מכאן ואוכלים, elu olim mikan ve’ochlim ve’elu
olim mikan ve’ochlim, you can actually eat fruit on the top of
it, right because that’s considered no man’s land and therefore you can
eat the fruit that’s already on the top of that wall, but
what you cannot do is you cannot take fruit off of the
wall into your courtyard.
So just to remind you, right, we had this before, you’ve
got these two courtyards, A and B, you’ve got this wall like
this between them, okay, so because it’s ten high, they’re two separate
courtyards. If it’s ten high and four wide, it’s its own רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid. so anything that’s here neither belongs to A or
to B and it’s okay in this separate space. But you can’t
take from the wall to A or from the wall to B
because that’s a separate domain that you haven’t made an עירוב eruv
for. All right, so that’s that.
Can you go up on top of the wall to eat it?
Yeah, I mean you can’t, I mean unless you got, I mean
because to bring it down to you is going from one domain
to the next. All right, so that’s that case there, right about
the stuff on the wall is okay. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: נפרצה כותל
עד עשר אמות, nifratza kosel ad eser amos, now if the wall
has a breach until עשר אמות, eser amos, that’s like an opening
and that gives you both
options. מערבין שנים ואם רצו מערבין אחד. me’arvin shnayim ve’im ratzu me’arvin
echad. You can choose to do two עירובים, eruvim, you can choose
to do one. מפני שהוא כפתח. mipnei shehu k’pesach. That’s like an
opening. יותר מכאן, yoseir mikan, if it’s more than עשר אמות, eser
amos, then it’s like there’s no wall at all and מערבין אחד
ואין מערבין שנים, me’arvin echad ve’ein me’arvin shnayim, then you need to
make one עירוב, eruv, you can’t make two. Okay, so the rest
is not relevant to us, what’s relevant is when the wall is
ten by four, it’s its own רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid, And what
then is also relevant is the discussion we had about that in
the גמרא. Gemara והוינן בה, ve’havinan boh, we asked on that way
back when we learned this, wasn’t so long ago, about a week
and a half about ten days ago. והוינן בה ve’havinan boh we
asked on it, this hopefully will be good חזרה chazara for everyone.
אין בו ארבעה מאי, ein bo arba’a mai, let’s say it’s not
four טפחים wide. Now if this wall is not four טפחים wide,
it divides the courtyards, but what is its status? If it’s not
four, it’s ten high and if it’s not four טפחים wide, what’s
its status? Ten high and less than four טפחים, anything basically less
than four טפחים wide is a מקום פטור. makom patur. Okay, so
what is the status of this מקום פטור makom patur we asked?
Because because it’s not its own מקום, makom, maybe it’s considered competed
territory between A and B and can’t be used at all. That’s
what we were debated, if you remember that. There was two positions
about that. Okay, והוינן בה, ve’havinan boh, אין בו ארבעה מאי, ein
bo arba’a mai, if it’s not four טפחים wide what’s the story?
אמר רב, amar Rav, אויר שתי רשויות שולט בו avir shtei reshuyos
sholet bo ולא יזיז. v’lo yaziz.
So רב Rav says, both A and B want to claim it.
It's not its own domain, it's a מקום פטור. makom patur. So
essentially it's being competed between A and B, and therefore, because it's
competed territory, you can't move even on top of the wall, even
a hair's breadth. You can't move at all because it's a space
that does not have an עירוב eiruv that has sort of competed,
you know, sort of domains on it. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר
amar no. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
it's not that it's both and a problem, it's either essentially. A
can use it and B can use it each one sequentially or
whatever, when they're using it claiming it to be theirs. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan אמר אלו מעלין מכאן ואוכלין, elu ma'alin mikan ve-ochlin, not
עולין olin but מעלין ma'alin can bring fruit up to the wall
or bring it down from the wall, ואלו מעלין מכאן ואוכלין ve-elu
ma'alin mikan ve-ochlin and these can bring it up. So what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says is, this is your standard מקום פטור makom
patur and the same way a מקום פטור makom patur in the
middle of a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim can be used by רשות
הרבים reshut ha-rabim and רשות היחיד, reshut ha-yachid so a מקום פטור
makom patur in the middle of two חצרות chatzerot that haven't made
an עירוב eiruv can be used from both חצרות, chatzerot, right? If
this was a מקום פטור makom patur and here was רשות היחיד
reshut ha-yachid and here was רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, you could put
packages on it on both sides. You wouldn't say it's competed territory.
So even when they're both רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid of the two
courtyards, each side can use it; it's a מקום פטור. makom patur.
That's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. Okay, but now the question
is: ואזל רבי יוחנן לטעמיה, ve-azal Rabbi Yochanan le-ta'ameih, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan goes according to his reasoning, דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי
יוחנן de-ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan because like we just
said a second
ago: מקום שאין בו ארבע על ארבע, makom she-ein bo arba al
arba, it's not four by four, מותר לבני רשות הרבים ולבני רשות
היחיד לכתף עליו. mutar li-vnei reshut ha-rabim u-li-vnei reshut ha-yachid le-katef alav.
You can put it from either רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid or רשות
הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, ובלבד שלא יחליפו, u-vilvad she-lo yachlifu, as long as
you don't use it as a way of getting through to the
other רשות. reshut. So what's the point of quoting all of this?
The point is to say, if you remember, the גמרא Gemara said,
one minute, how are you allowed to cheat and use the banks
here to get to the כרמלית? karmelit? You're not allowed to cheat
through a מקום פטור. makom patur. And the answer was, oh this
is only a rabbinic issue because it's only a כרמלית. karmelit. But
one minute, up here by the two courtyards, it's also a rabbinic
issue. Carrying from one רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid, to another רשות היחיד,
Reshus HaYachid all of the discussion of עירוב, eiruv, right, is a
complete rabbinic issue. And nevertheless, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you can
put stuff on it, but he never said you can go from
here, something that was put on by B and take it into
A, or vice-versa. So even with the rabbinic domains, you cannot use
a מקום פטור makom patur as a way station to go through
it. So how again can you use the banks, if that's what's
actually going on here, as a way of getting into the כרמלית?
karmelit? So let's see. So the גמרא Gemara says: הא זעירי אמרה.
ha Ze'iri amrah. Okay, fine. So according to רב דימי, Rav Dimi,
it's true that you're not allowed to use a מקום פטור makom
patur as a way
to, one minute,
one minute, oh I'm sorry, the other way. According to זעירי, Ze'iri,
זעירי Ze'iri was the one who said that, who said this in
the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. We had quoted it in
the name of רב דימי, Rav Dimi, but in fact, I mean,
or just straight רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but זעירי Ze'iri is the
one who says that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would not let you
go from A to B. But actually, according to רב דימי, Rav
Dimi, who is the one if you remember who earlier quoted רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, he actually would let you go via a מקום
פטור makom patur into a כרמלית. karmelit. So the גמרא's Gemara basic
answer is, right now it's really only problem is that it's inconsistent
with statements of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But it's not actually bothered
with the position itself. And the גמרא's Gemara actually at this stage
asserting yes, this idea that we have this question about three or
four, we're going to stick with our explanation. And the idea is
that if this is a מקום פטור makom patur as the banks,
then you can use it via the מקום פטור makom patur to
get into the water and to go to a כרמלית. karmelit. Even
though normally we say you cannot do it via מקום פטור, makom
patur, this would be a position of רב דימי Rav Dimi that
would say that if it's only a rabbinic רשות reshut it would
be allowed. So let's just finish the other opinion. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this: ול... קשיא... so one
minute, הא זעירי Ze'iri אמרה. ולזעירי קשיא. u-le-Ze'iri kashya. But one minute,
at least זעירי Ze'iri says, the way the גמרא's Gemara trying to
limit this contradiction, at least זעירי now we're claiming says you can't
go through a מקום פטור makom patur even into a rabbinic domain.
So if he says that by the two courtyards, he should say
the same by the banks of this aqueduct. So the גמרא Gemara
says, and therefore back to the question: how can you use the
banks of the aqueduct to get access if that's what's actually going
on? So the גמרא Gemara says: הא זעירי מוקים לה באמת המים
גופה ורב דימי תנאי היא. ha Ze'iri mokim lah be-amat ha-mayim gufah
ve-Rav Dimi tana'ei hi. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, remember what
we first tried to say. What we first tried to say is
that the question of three or four isn't about the banks, it's
about actually the aqueduct itself. And that actually maybe there would be
an opinion that would say that for it to not be a
כרמלית, karmelit, it's not enough that it's less than four, it actually
has to be less than
three. So what the גמרא Gemara has now said is this issue,
I know this is getting a little bit sloppy, okay try to
draw it more descriptively, right this issue that you have a house
A
and house B, and you've got this, you know, כרמלית Carmelit going
through it, and we said this sort of river, and we said
that if it is less than three or less than four it's
okay, we have two explanations. One is if this is less than
three or four, the actual river itself or the aqueduct itself, it
stops being a כרמלית, Carmelit, and that that means that the whether
the minimum size of a כרמלית Carmelit is three or four is
a debate, even though before we wanted to say everybody said the
minimum size is four. And the other explanation is that it's not
about that, but it's about whether the banks are three or four
and that the banks are a מקום פטור makom patur and that
A, the size of a מקום פטור makom patur is debated as
three or four, as opposed to being less than four, which we've
always said, and B, that you can go through a מקום פטור
makom patur into a כרמלית, Carmelit, which is something that we normally
have not said, but now we're saying there would be an opinion
that would say it. So the
two explanations which I must admit are weak because both of them
assume that basic numbers that we've always assumed to be very clear,
that a minimum size of a כרמלית Carmelit is four, a minimum
size of less than four of מקום פטור makom patur is less
than four, we're now saying is being debated. So the גמרא Gemara.
finally has a third explanation which is much better, which gets to
the לבוד Lavud issue which seems anyway to have been the debate.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says: ותיהוי
כחורי כרמלית. ve-tehei ke-chorei Carmelit. One minute, says the גמרא. Gemara I
don't get why this whole thing is an issue. Why can't they
be like the holes of a כרמלית? Carmelit? Now what does that
mean? So if you... you might remember that if you've got a
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim here, a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim is running
alongside a wall and the wall has little holes in it, okay,
that these holes in the wall are also considered part of the
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim because they're used by the people in the
רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. Similarly would be true if you had holes
in a wall inside of a house, but it's a bigger חידוש
chiddush by רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. So little things that are serving
it, you know, think about also the sidewalks, actually that's called צידי
רשות הרבים. tziddei reshut ha-rabim. But things that might not be the
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim proper that serve it are considered connected to
the רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. So the way רש״י Rashi explains this
question, the question is how do you call this a כרמלית? Carmelit?
Maybe it's true that when it gets between the houses it's less
than three or four, but presumably when it gets out into the
bigger world it's larger. So here down here it's a כרמלית, Carmelit,
then even when it narrows it should be like those little holes
in the wall and it should retain the definition of a כרמלית.
Carmelit. Okay, that's the way רש״י understands the question. There are other
understandings, but that's the way רש״י understands it. So why doesn't that
work? I mean why is three or four relevant? Isn't this just
a piece of a larger כרמלית? Carmelit? So the גמרא Gemara says:
ותיהוי כחורי כרמלית אביי בר אבין ורב חנינא בר אבין דאמרי תרווייהו.
ve-tehei ke-chorei Carmelit Abbaye bar Avin ve-Rav Chanina bar Avin de-amrei tarvayeihu.
So they both said: אין חורין לכרמלית. ein chorin le-Carmelit. No.
By biblical רשויות reshuyot we'll say that the little attendant things are
part of the רשות, reshut, but by a כרמלית Carmelit we'll be
more lenient. So since here it gets to be narrow enough, four
really is the number, but according to this or less than three,
then at least here it's no longer a כרמלית Carmelit even if
down here it is a כרמלית. Carmelit. Okay. Now, but now the
debate we've said about this aqueduct is either that there's a debate
whether the minimum size of a כרמלית Carmelit is three or four,
although we've always said four, or there's a debate whether the minimum
size of a מקום פטור makom patur is less than three or
four, although again we've always said four. So the גמרא gemara says...
I'm sorry, I keep waiting to get the last answer. There's one
more answer about the holes of the כרמלית. Carmelit. רב אשי אמר
אפילו תימא יש חורין לכרמלית, Rav Ashi amar afilu teima yesh chorin
le-Carmelit, even if normally you say that a כרמלית Carmelit does have
holes, meaning things that are offshoots are part of it, הני מילי
בסמוכה. hani milei be-smucha. That's if it's right next to it. הכא
במופלגת. hacha be-mupleget. Here it's very distant. Meaning, you know, if you've
got a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim and the wall right alongside has
a little hole, then that hole is part of the רשות הרבים.
reshut ha-rabim. But here down here it's a כרמלית, Carmelit, but you
know if it narrows like this, and the next where it really
starts being a כרמלית Carmelit is way down here, so when you
get all the way over here, quite a distance from where the
actual כרמלית Carmelit is, it's no longer going to be considered part
of the כרמלית. Carmelit. exactly but if it really did widen right
afterwards
i mean right it’s
not exactly clear how close is close anyway that answers the question
of why this is not considered a כרמלית Carmelis when it gets
narrow but we still have to understand this debate of three or
four there are two explanations again are minimum size of a כרמלית
Carmelis or minimum size of a מקום פטור Mokom Patur and now
finally the גמרא gemara has what i consider to be the most
straightforward answer רבינא אמר כגון דעביד ליה נפיקי אפוני Ravina amar kagon
d'avid lei nifik apuni we’re not talking about banks we’re not talking
about the width we’re not talking about walls what happened was is
you’ve got
you’ve got your houses here right and this thing is running through
it and you’re trying to satisfy what the משנה Mishna said the
משנה Mishna said is you’ve got to make walls right so what
you did is you made here little walls you just didn’t make
them all the way across okay this actually would have to be
according to the משנה Mishna in you know into the you know
in the depth underneath the bank in order for it to be
good unless it’s רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the there’s a gap
between the walls right and the gap is three or four טפחים
and the question is is that you know is that gap considered
closed so it’s basically a debate of לבוד Lavud what’s the minimum
לבוד Lavud three or four and that we know is debated so
he says you’re getting yourself so you know tied up in knots
he says it’s just a simple issue of when do we think
like a gap is closed why do we see that again over
here i don’t know ואזדו רבנן לטעמייהו ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל לטעמיה
Ve'azdu rabbonan l'taimeihu v'Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel l'taimei everybody goes according to
their normal position we know these two תנאים Tanaim always debate i
mean this is why it was so crazy רבנן Rabbonan said three
less than three רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel said
less than four we know from other places that they debate exactly
this three or four by לבוד so that you turned it to
yourself in knots to say the debate was about מקום פטור Mokom
Patur or כרמלית Carmelis no make it into some scenario where they’re
debating about closing up a wall and whether the minimum is three
or four i understand the problem Michael says why repeat it but
at least it’s a much more straightforward read and doesn’t challenge a
whole range of basic assumptions okay so that’s the end of that
that’s putting in the wall into the aqueduct this next משנה Mishna
we’ve now quoted multiple times and this is the balcony over the
water and making the box around the balcony making the מחיצות Mechitzos
to view it as though it goes down into the water גזוסטרא
שהיא למעלה מן המים Gezustra shehi lemala min hamayim so you have
a balcony some protrusion above the water אין ממלאין הימנה בשבת Ein
memalin mimena b'Shabbos you cannot fill up you know you’ve got a
hole in it you cannot lower the bucket down and fill up
from it
אלא אם כן עשו לה מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים Ella im kein
asu lah mechitza gevoha asara tefachim בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה bein mimalah
bein mimalata whether above or below again we’ve seen this multiple times
just to visualize it once again now i’m a dangerous man with
my marker here you’ve got this thing the water runs underneath you
want to basically lower down a bucket problem is that this is
a כרמלית Carmelis this because it’s somehow attached to your house is
part of the רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid so how do you do
that you make walls either below or above and those walls imaginarily
extend down and therefore makes the area directly underneath it a רשות
היחיד okay
now בין מלמטה bein mimalata וכן שתי גזוסטראות זו למעלה מזו V'chen
shtei gezustraot zo lemala mizo if you have two of these protrusions
one higher than the other they’re not on top of one another
they’re set off so עשו לעליונה ולא עשו לתחתונה asu l'elyona v'lo
asu l'tachtona the top one made the walls and the bottom one
did not so the bottom one can’t use their own but you
might think that the top people can use theirs no שתיהן אסורות
עד שיערבו shteihen asurot ad sheyei'arvu they have to make an עירוב
Eiruv and we’ve this one we’re not going to look at again
but we discussed this at extension you know extensively last time the
idea was was that it’s considered to be if you’ve got two
of them right and these guys did it so you would think
it at least and these guys did not you would think it
at least works for these guys but no assuming there’s some form
of access there’s a ladder or it’s close and they can jump
so it’s like they’re both competing for the same space and they
have to make an עירוב Eiruv that gets back to this issue
of a space that’s being equally competed okay so that’s an עירוב
Eiruv issue that we’ve that we dealt with before let’s take a
look now at the walls around the hole and using it to
draw water מתניתין דלא כחנניה בן עקביא Masnisin d'lo k'Chananya Ben Akavya
okay remember חנניה Chananya so our משנה Mishna that requires actual walls
for this hole for this sort of balcony is not like
חנניה דתניא D'tanya we taught in a ברייתא Braisa חנניה בן עקביא
אומר גזוסטרא שיש בה ארבע על ארבע אמות חוקק בה ארבע על
ארבע וממלא Chananya Ben Akavya omer gezustra sheyesh bah arba al arba
amos chokek bah arba al arba umemalei you make a hole in
the middle and you can fill it and you view it as
if the rest of the of the plank you know bends down
so our משנה Mishna did give that option. Clearly our משנה mishna
holds that you need real walls. So the גמרא thankfully is not
going to do the whole math again about, you know, interestingly placed
planks. Okay. אמר רב יוחנן משום רבי יוסי, amar Rav Yochanan mishum
Rabbi Yose, but it is going to clarify the statements made before.
אמר רב יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן זמרא, amar Rav Yochanan mishum
Rabbi Yose ben Zimra, לא התיר רבי חנניה בן עקביא אלא בים
של טבריה. lo hitir Rabbi Chananya ben Akavia ela be-yam shel Tverya.
So he only allowed it over the Kinneret, over the ocean, the
lake of Tiberias. הואיל ויש לה אוגניים ועיירות וכרפיפות מקיפות אותה. hoil
ve-yesh la ognayim ve-ayarot ve-karfifot makifot otah. Since it has banks and
like villages and, you know, yards that surround it. Again, how all
of those make it special is not so clear, but nevertheless it
was a special allowance around the Lake Kinneret. He would not have
this imaginary walls by other types of bodies of waters. אבל בשאר
מים לא, aval bi-shar mayim lo, not by other things. And now
the גמרא actually since we're talking about a special, you know, allowance
that חנניה בן עקביא made for טבריה, Tverya, we're going to actually
digress a little and talk about other rulings he made for the
people of Tiberias. So תנו רבנן tanu rabanan we saw, ג' דברים
התיר רבי חנניה בן עקביא לאנשי טבריה. gimmel devarim hitir Rabbi Chananya
ben Akavia le-anshei Tverya. He allowed three things for the people of
Tiberias. התיר I'm sorry, skipped a line. התיר רבי לאנשי טבריה ממלאין
מים מגזוסטרא בשבת. memalin mayim mi-gizustra be-Shabbat, You can raise water, draw
water from the protrusion. Now of course the חכמים Chachamim allow it
as well, but he allowed it even though there weren't real walls
around it, even though it was just a big plank. וטומנין באצה,
ve-tomnin be-atza, and you can bury fruit in like the
pods of, like, of legumes. We'll talk about what that means. ומסתפגין
באלונטית, ve-mistapgin be-aluntit, and you can dry yourself with towels on שבת
Shabbat or יום טוב Yom Tov and we're not afraid you'll come
to squeeze them. So these are three leniencies. Now we're going to
go through them. ממלאין מים מגזוסטרא בשבת, הא דאמרן. ha de-amran. So
to draw water from this protrusion, this balcony, we said that. That
his leniency was you don't need real walls, you can imaginarily bend
the walls around the hole in order to get the water. וטומנין
באצה מאי היא? ve-tomnin be-atza mai hi? What is this thing about
burying fruit or, you know, in a food in these pods? דתניא,
de-tanya, השכים להביא פסולת. hishkim le-havi psola. If somebody gets up early
in the morning to bring the, you know, to collect out of
the yard the whatever the
psola. Anyway, the non-food part of these legumes that was left out
there in the yard. So אם בשביל שיהא עליו טל, im bishvil
she-yehe alav tal, if the reason you got up early in the
morning to collect them was because you wanted them moist, הרי הוא
בכי יותן. harei hu be-chi yutan. It's considered like you wanted the
water on it. As you remember, I'm sure, that food does not
is not susceptible to become טמא tamei unless water goes on it
after it's picked and unless you want the water to go on
it. So what you did is you went out in the fields
to collect this stuff which was the leftover of the legumes that
you collected and dew had fallen on it. Why did you go
up so early in the morning? If it's because you wanted them
moist, then the dew is there for your desire and it makes
it susceptible for טומאה. tumah. ואם בשביל שלא יתבטל ממלאכתו, ve-im bishvil
she-lo yitbatel mi-malachto, but if the reason you did it early in
the morning was because you had a whole day of work ahead
of you so that, you know, you got to do it before,
you know, early on in the day, אינו בכי יותן. eino be-chi
yutan. Then it's not like you wanted the water there, it's immaterial
to you, you just wanted to do it
early. וסתם אנשי טבריה, ve-stam anshei Tverya, it's really true about everybody,
but as it ends, the normal reality of the people of Tiberias,
כמי שלא יתבטל ממלאכתו דמי. ki-mi she-lo yitbatel mi-malachto dami. They had
a very, I don't know, Protestant work ethic or they had a
lot of work to do, and therefore the reason they got up
nice and early was clearly because they had a full day of
work ahead of them. So what does the issue mean? So רש"י
Rashi says therefore the question is if you put fruit to keep
it warm inside of these pods, is the fruit susceptible for טומאה
tumah or not? And therefore since and when it says that they
would put fruit in it, it meant they put fruit in it
with no concern of טומאה. tumah. Because the dew that was on
these pods was not considered there for their desire and therefore there
was no concerns of טומאה tumah and we will find out tomorrow
about drying themselves with towels on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom
Tov.